Now, I want to um go into something completely
different. Critics have long pointed to CIA
linked operations intersecting with cocaine
trafficking from Latin America during the Cold War
and with opium networks in Afghanistan after 2001.
So, what's your take on that? Yeah, it's correct.
That's immoral. Let's talk Let's talk about
cocaine first. Created a huge problem in the
US in the 80s. Gigantic problem in the US. It
led to the crack epidemic. Yeah. So, the CIA
still to this day denies that it had anything
to do with cocaine trafficking. That's a lie.
It's hard to explain. So, so there there
was a reporter for the Sacramento B,
I think it was, uh, Gary Webb. Uh Gary Webb was
on to this story that the CIA was shipping cocaine
to the United States in the 1980s, the early
1980s, and using the money from the cocaine
to buy weapons for the Contra rebels who
were fighting in Nicaragua. That was true.
There was one minor detail that he got wrong,
and this is what the CIA has hung its hat on ever
since. There were two separate groups of Contraore
rebels. one in the north and one in the south.
The US was arming the group
in the north. In the south,
they were selling cocaine and they were using
the money from the cocaine to arm themselves.
The CIA allowed the trans shshipment of the
cocaine through the north and into the United
States. So, was it the CIA's cocaine? Not really.
Not technically, but the CIA still allowed the
cocaine to come into the United States. totally
immoral and illegal. It's actually a death penalty
case to import large amounts of drugs like
that. Gary Webb um stumbled on this story and
the minor detail that he got wrong was he didn't
realize there were two separate Contra groups.
He ended up committing suicide um on the very
same day. Listen to this for a coincidence.
On the very same day, the Washington Post and the
New York Times wrote nearly identical articles
saying, "Gary web's a liar. Gary Webb's a phony.
He made the whole thing up. None of this is true."
He was fired from his job uh at the newspaper
and then bounced around from little unknown
newspaper to little unknown newspaper. And then
finally, in a state of depression, he committed
suicide in a motel room in Colorado. Maybe
maybe he didn't commit suicide. I don't know.
Uh but he was right. The CIA was at the very
least allowing the importation of cocaine,
which led to the crack epidemic. It was it
was the CIA cocaine that was turned into
crack first in Oakland, California, later in
uh Los Angeles that began then sweeping east
until, you know, 1985 it arrived in Washington.
And Washington, Baltimore, Philadelphia, New York
had the highest murder rates in the history of the
country. The whole country went crazy over crack.
I've talked about heroin a lot. So in
the last year of Taliban rule before 911,
Afghanistan produced zero heroin, nothing. Um the
Afghans actually were net food exporters in 2000
and the first half of 2001. But by the
time the United States invaded and occupied
uh Afghanistan, it was producing 93% of the
world's heroin. So to make a long story short,
when I was the senior investigator on
the Senate Foreign Relations Committee,
I told John Kerry, I want to go to Afghanistan and
do an in-depth Senate study on heroin trafficking.
And so I went to Afghanistan. Nobody wanted to
help me. It's the only time in my career I ever
pulled rank on someone. As a senior congressional
staffer, I had the rank of Brigadier General. Oh.
And I always felt kind of weird about that. And
I I never used it for anything until this trip.
I I went to Bagram Air Base outside of Kabull
and I told them and I had cabled them in advance.
I said, "I want to go to Kandahar. I want to
go to Helmund to Lashkar and then back to uh
Bagram." And they said, "No, no, can't do it.
Too dangerous." I said, "Bullshit. You do this
all the time. Literally every day." "No, can't
do it. You're a civilian." And I said, "No, I
have the rank of Brigadier General. I'm not asking
you. I'm telling you, you will fly me to Kandahar
and then to Lashkar and then come back." And so,
okay. Okay. They agreed. So, I go to Kandahar.
We have meetings there for half the day. We
fly to Lashkar. As you're flying into Lashkar,
all you can see for miles around is poppy.
Nothing but poppy, like an ocean of poppy.
And this village is in the middle of this ocean of
poppy. So I said, I want to drive into the poppy
fields and talk to a a farmer. They hated that
idea. But we got into two jeeps. We had security.
I had a translator. And sure enough, we find a
poppy farmer in his field. So, I go to talk to him
and I asked him what turned out to be a naive
question. I said, 'Why do you grow poppy
when you can grow things that have two growing
seasons like onions or pomegranates? And he goes,
"The Americans told me in 2001 that if I told them
where the Arabs were, I could grow all the poppy
I wanted." I said, "What Americans told you you
could grow poppy?" And my military handler says,
"Meeting's over." He pulled me by the arm.
Meeting's over. We're under threat. We have to
get back to Bagram. He did it on purpose. So, we
get back to the helicopter. We fly back to Bagram.
I I fly back to Washington. I
write this paper, in-depth paper.
And I had a friend at the Drug Enforcement
Administration. So, I I called him
and I said, "I'm going to send you a paper that
I just wrote, eyes only. don't tell anybody,
but I want your thoughts before I publish it."
So, he calls me back, I don't know, 3 days later,
and he said, "Buddy, you know, you're never going
to get this published, right?" And I said, "Why?"
And he said, "Afghanistan produces 93% of the
world's heroin. Almost all of that heroin goes to
Iran and Russia, and we want them to be addicted
to heroin. It makes their societies weaker.
He was right. (Senator John) Kerry never allowed
me to publish it because the CIA told Kerry not
to allow me to publish it. And uh and then we
have to ask ourselves, you know, 10 years later,
15 years later, the same question. Why won't the
Chinese stop the flow of fentanyl exactly into
the United States? Because they want us to be
addicted to fentanyl. It makes our society weaker.
Very very very interesting what you just
said and it's so true. You're right.
Yeah. I mean who who doesn't have a friend or
relative that's died of a fentanyl overdose
in the US? I have three friends who've lost
children to fentanyl. Really? Three. Mhm.
But isn't fentanyl also produced
inside the US by the Sackler family?
That's medical fentanyl. But they also use that
and get addicted to it. That's different. They get
to it by the doctors. They get addicted to it and
then that's how they turn to the other one. Right.
In some cases. Yes. And and that's how that's
how that's how that family has they've lost
I mean they were fined a billion dollars in a
class action suit. Yes. U their name has been
stripped off of museums. Yeah. But the fentanyl
that the Chinese are producing and a lot of it
is Chinese-owned and it's produced in Mexico and
smuggled across the border. Um, a lot of it is
so potent that there have been there have been
examples of police officers who have fainted
just from being in the presence of fentanyl and
they have to be given Narcan to bring them back.
Oh wow. Yeah. It's completely unregulated. It's
just you never know. a good friend of mine. Um,
oh, and this just he he he's just
spilled his soul on Facebook about this.
He wasn't getting along with his daughter for
years. It was a bitter divorce. His daughter
was with the mother. Finally, as an adult, they
finally forge a relationship. They become very
close. She tells him she's going to meet friends
out at a bar in Washington. Two hours later, she's
dead. Oh. Because somebody offered a little bit
of cocaine, it turned out to have fentanyl in it.
It killed her instantly. Oh god. Oh god. And
this happens every day in America. So sad.